{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "During World War II, this character's comic strip recruited children into metal recycling crews known as the Junior Commandos. This character was named after a James Whitcomb Riley poem by her creator, cartoonist Harold Gray. For 10 points, name this character who, in a musical adaptation, sings about her \"Hard Knock Life\" and \"Tomorrow.\"",
      "answer": "Little Orphan Annie"
    },
    {
      "question": "Joseph Haydn composed pieces in this genre named for \"a time of war\" and Horatio Nelson. Leoš Janáček (lay-OHSH yuh-NAH-chek) used a dead Slavonic language to create the \"Glagolitic\" example of this form, which was used for a piece in B minor by J.S. Bach. For 10 points, name this genre which sets the \"Kyrie\" (KEER-ee-ay), \"Credo,\" and other parts of a liturgy.",
      "answer": "mass"
    },
    {
      "question": "This specific location is where the Perserschutt, a dump of destroyed ceremonial artifacts, was buried. The Sacred Way ran between Eleusis and the Propylaea, a gate that controlled entrance to this specific location. Many structures in this specific place, including the Erechtheum, were reconstructed by Phidias at the behest of Pericles. For 10 points, name this hill in Athens, the location of the Parthenon.",
      "answer": "the Acropolis of Athens"
    },
    {
      "question": "Gustave de Beamount and Alexis de Tocqueville originally went to the U.S. to observe these facilities, thoguh Tocqueville wrote Democracy in America instead. Jeremy Bentham proposed the \"panopticon\" design for these facilities. For 10 points, name these facilities which penologists study and which have been home to John Dillinger and Charles Manson.",
      "answer": "prisons"
    },
    {
      "question": "This President lost several Cabinet members, including Secretary of State Abel Upshur, when a cannon exploded on the USS Princeton. He refused to open mail addressed to the \"Acting President\" after he took office following the death of his popular war hero predecessor. For 10 points, name this man who completed the Presidential term of William Henry Harrison.",
      "answer": "John Tyler"
    },
    {
      "question": "Members of this group built Bodrum Castle, partly from the ruins of the Mausoleum of Halicarnassus. This organization lost Malta after refusing to let Napoleon’s fleet enter its port. Earlier, they lost the island of Rhodes to Suleiman the Magnificent after a 1522 siege. For 10 points, name this crusading order named for their original mandate of caring for the sick.",
      "answer": "Knights Hospitaller"
    },
    {
      "question": "A major doctrinal influence on this group was Joseph Franklin Rutherford, who reformed the Bible Student associations and promoted its belief that Jesus was crucified on a tree rather than a cross. This group, which traces its founding to Charles Taze Russell, published The Watchtower. For 10 points, name this sect known for proselytizing and not accepting blood donations.",
      "answer": "Jehovah's Witnesses"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a painting of this man by Paolo Veronese, the old woman Sisygambis confusedly addresses this man’s close friend Hephaestion while begging for mercy. In a depiction of this ruler, a giant scroll in Latin describing the casualties of the battle flies over the two armies fighting. For 10 points, name this Macedonian king who was depicted fighting Darius III in The Battle of Issus.",
      "answer": "Alexander the Great"
    },
    {
      "question": "These people, who acquired a cult following after the discovery of the \"Joplin photos,\" worked with Ralph Fults and Henry Methvin prior to their death in Bienville, Louisiana. A landmark 1967 film about these people starred Faye Dunaway and Warren Beatty. For 10 points, identify this 1930s criminal pair who were killed in a shootout with police.",
      "answer": "Bonnie Parker and Clyde Barrow"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man advocated the \"full dinner pail\" in his second \"front porch campaign\" under the management of Mark Hanna. This man was advised not to go to the Temple of Music at the Pan- American Exposition in Buffalo, where he was fatally shot by Leon Czolgosz (CHOLE-gosh). For 10 points, name this President whose death was followed by the rise of Theodore Roosevelt.",
      "answer": "William McKinley NHBB B 2014-2015"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1992, this agency launched a program to certify electronic devices, most visibly computer monitors, as efficient, known as EnergyStar. A program administered by this government agency has targeted sites such as Love Canal and is known as Superfund. For 10 points, name this agency created by Richard Nixon that enforces the Clean Water Act and similar laws.",
        "answer": "EPA"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Love Canal crisis occurred during the Presidency of what man, who also installed solar panels on the roof of the White House?",
        "answer": "Jimmy Carter"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man's paper On the Description of Oval Curves came out when he was just 14. He created the first color photograph after showing the primacy of the RGB color system. His distribution of gas molecules was combined with the work of Ludwig Boltzmann. For 10 points, name this physicist who determined that light is a wave and formulated laws of electromagnetism.",
        "answer": "James Clerk Maxwell"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "\"Maxwell's addition\" modified the circuit law discovered by what French namesake of the SI unit of electric current?",
        "answer": "Andre-Marie Ampere"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city is where the mathematician Hypatia (high-PAY-shuh) was killed by a mob. The Septuagint (sep-TOO-uh-jint) was created in this city, which was home to the largest population of Jews in the world in the first and second centuries BC. For 10 points, name this city which was home to a notable \"library\" and \"lighthouse\" in Classical Egypt.",
        "answer": "Alexandria"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What other wonder of the ancient world was built near a harbor to commemorate a victory in the Wars of the Diadochi (dee-AH-doh-kee)?",
        "answer": "Colossus of Rhodes"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The losing Democratic candidate in this state's 2014 race sought to become the first Iraq war veteran to serve as a governor and lost to a ticket containing Boyd Rutherford, the third straight black lieutenant governor in this state. For 10 points, name this state where Anthony Brown lost in an upset to Republican Lawrence Hogan in a bid to succeed Martin O'Malley as governor.",
        "answer": "Maryland"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Anthony Brown's wife is the director of government relations for what media conglomerate, the owner of NBC and Universal Studios, which entered FCC scrutiny in 2014 after announcing plans to purchase Time Warner Cable?",
        "answer": "Comcast"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country was the destination of Operation Provide Relief and Operation Restore Hope. The U.S. intervened in this country following the fall of the Siad Barre (see-ODD bah-RAY) regime. A disastrous mission in this country's capital involved two Black Hawk helicopters being shot down. For 10 points, name this country where the U.S. fought the Battle of Mogadishu.",
        "answer": "Somalia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which two European countries colonized the territory that makes up present-day Somalia?",
        "answer": [
          "Italy and the United Kingdom",
          "England, Britain, UK,",
          "Great Britain too"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This leader mediated the Mediterranean Agreements of 1887. His struggle against the Catholic Church throughout the 1870s was known as the Kulturkampf. He instigated a war to take Schleswig and Holstein from Denmark, and used the Ems Dispatch to trigger the Franco- Prussian War. For 10 points, name this Prussian statesman who united the German Empire.",
        "answer": "Otto von Bismarck"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Bismarck was forced to resign as chancellor by which German Emperor?",
        "answer": "Wilhelm II"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 2009, voters approved an amendment in this organization's constitution that replaced the unanimity requirement with a “double majority” requirement for many policies. The Maastricht Treaty created this group and gave the criteria necessary for countries to adopt its common currency. For 10 points, name this organization of sovereign states, many of whom use the euro.",
        "answer": "European Union"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What capital city was the namesake for the treaty signed in 2007 and approved in 2009 that changed the voting procedure for the Council of Ministers?",
        "answer": "Lisbon"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Mark Kurlansky's popular-press World History of this good describes how the Taghaza mine produced it in the medieval Sahara desert. This chemical compound was traded in silence in pre- modern West Africa, where its value per pound was equal to a pound of gold. For 10 points, name this mineral which was useful for preserving meat and balancing diets.",
        "answer": "rock salt"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What empire, which presided over the salt-for-gold trade from Kumbi Saleh, had its name adopted by Kwame Nkrumah for the post-independence Gold Coast?",
        "answer": "Ghana Empire NHBB B 2014-2015"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "ALASKA",
      "prompt": "Name the alaska...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Admitted to the U.S. in 1959, eight months before what 50th state?",
          "answer": "Hawaii"
        },
        {
          "question": "The home of Larry Sanger, who co-founded what online encyclopedia with Jimbo Wales?",
          "answer": "Wikipedia"
        },
        {
          "question": "The site of a 1964 earthquake which struck on what holiday two days before Easter?",
          "answer": "Good Friday"
        },
        {
          "question": "The site of a 1989 disaster when what oil company's tanker Valdez crashed on Prince William Sound?",
          "answer": "Exxon"
        },
        {
          "question": "The destination of the central animated family, which flees Springfield, in what 2007 film?",
          "answer": "The Simpsons Movie"
        },
        {
          "question": "Represented in the Senate from 1968 to 2009 by what longest-tenured Republican Senator ever?",
          "answer": "Ted Stevens"
        },
        {
          "question": "Embarrassed when that Senator used what three-word phrase to describe the Internet in a 2006 viral video?",
          "answer": "\"series of tubes\""
        },
        {
          "question": "Home to a proposed accessway to Gravina Island which received what derogatory nickname in a 2006 debate over pork-barrel spending?",
          "answer": "\"bridge to nowhere\""
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "BLACK DEATH",
      "prompt": "During the bubonic plague of the 14th century, which…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "flea-ridden rodent helped spread disease?",
          "answer": "black rats"
        },
        {
          "question": "religious group was targeted by pogroms after false accusations of well-poisoning?",
          "answer": "Jews"
        },
        {
          "question": "kingdom lost its king Alfonso XI, and later unified with Aragon to form Spain?",
          "answer": "Castille"
        },
        {
          "question": "group of religious fanatics travelled around whipping themselves?",
          "answer": "Flagellants"
        },
        {
          "question": "French city was Pope Clement VI living in thanks to the \"Babylonian captivity\"?",
          "answer": "Avignon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Italian author described people fleeing from the plague in his Decameron?",
          "answer": "Giovanni Boccaccio"
        },
        {
          "question": "English king, succeeded by Richard II, passed the Statute of Labourers?",
          "answer": "Edward III"
        },
        {
          "question": "Italian city, the home of the Doria family, was the destination of infected sailors from its port of Caffa?",
          "answer": "Genoa"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "ELECTION OF 1948",
      "prompt": "In the U.S. Presidential election of 1948, who...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was re-elected despite an erroneous Chicago Tribune headline?",
          "answer": "Harry Truman"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the Republican who lost the election, also in contradiction to the headline?",
          "answer": "Thomas Dewey"
        },
        {
          "question": "Declined an offer to run but became the winning Republican candidate four years later?",
          "answer": "Dwight Eisenhower"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the out-of-power British Conservative who lost an election after winning World War II, to whom the incumbent was frequently compared?",
          "answer": "Winston Churchill"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ran as the Dixiecrat candidate prior to becoming a long-serving South Carolina Senator?",
          "answer": "Strom Thurmond"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ran for the Progressive Party after serving as FDR's second Vice-President?",
          "answer": "Henry Wallace"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the body attacked as \"do-nothing\" by the winning candidate?",
          "answer": "U.S. Congress"
        },
        {
          "question": "Finished second at the Republican convention and was an isolationist Ohio Senator?",
          "answer": "Robert Taft NHBB B 2014-2015"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Along with “liberty,” this good names the Russian revolutionary group that split into the People’s Will and Black Repartition. Economist Henry George proposed a single tax on this good and the abolition of all other taxes in his book (20 pts)",
        "Progress and Poverty. The 18th- century French economic school known as (10 pts)",
        "Physiocracy argued that wealth was entirely derived from development of this good. For 10 points, name this good necessary for farming."
      ],
      "answer": "land"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This woman signed herself \"FWOTSC\" in a letter objecting to the term \"nine old men.\" This woman was the majority leader of the Arizona State Senate prior to her appointment to the (20 pts)",
        "Maricopa County Superior Court in 1975. She was replaced by Samuel Alito after retiring in 2005. She was nominated in 1981 to take the seat of (10 pts)",
        "Potter Stewart, by President Reagan. For 10 points, name this first woman to serve on the U.S. Supreme Court."
      ],
      "answer": "Sandra Day O'Connor"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This loser of the Battle of Valcour Island fell under suspicion for marrying Peggy Shippen. This man supported Ethan Allen's Green Mountain Boys in the capture of Fort (20 pts)",
        "Ticonderoga and was a key American presence at the Battle of (10 pts)",
        "Saratoga. Later, this man conspired with John Andre to surrender West Point. For 10 points, identify this American Revolutionary War general whose name is now synonymous with treason."
      ],
      "answer": "Benedict Arnold"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country celebrates the two-week-long Dashain (DAH-shayn) festival every fall. In the 1980s, this country took in over a hundred thousand Lhotshampa (LOTE-sahm-pa) refugees. This country has been subject to unrest in the (20 pts)",
        "Terai (teh-RYE) region, which it shares with India, and it was the only officially (10 pts)",
        "Hindu country in the world until its monarchy was abolished in 2008. For 10 points, name this Himalayan country governed from Kathmandu."
      ],
      "answer": "Nepal"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The winner of this sporting event is awarded the Harley J. Earl Trophy, and Sterling Marlin is the most recent back-to-back winner, doing so in 1994 and 1995. Dale (20 pts)",
        "Jarrett is the most recent to win it from the pole. Its 2014 winner was Dale (10 pts)",
        "Earnhardt Jr., who drove the #21 Chevrolet to Victory Lane. For 10 points, name this automobile race, the first event in NASCAR's annual Sprint Cup series, and which takes place at a namesake track in Northern Florida."
      ],
      "answer": "Daytona 500"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Like Pope Pius IX, this leader was presented with a Golden Telephone by the ITT Corporation, and this man imprisoned the leaders of the Conspiracy of the Pure. This man came to power after cancelling an election in which he was opposed by the Orthodox Party and the Authentic Party. This man overthrew (20 pts)",
        "Gerardo Machado as leader of the Sargents’ Revolt, and was overthrown by the (10 pts)",
        "July 26th movement. For 10 points, name this dictator of Cuba overthrown by Fidel Castro."
      ],
      "answer": "Fulgencio Batista y Zaldívar"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An extensive study of these people was compiled by Thomas McKenney and James Hall in the 1830s. These people are the subject of Helen Hunt Jackson's book A Century of Dishonor. Scott O'Dell wrote about a woman from this general group of people in (20 pts)",
        "Island of the Blue Dolphins, and these general people are the subjects of most books by (10 pts)",
        "Vine Deloria and Sherman Alexie. For 10 points, name these people who appear in pre- Columbian North American histories."
      ],
      "answer": "American Indians"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Critic Fred Hobson mused that this technology would have made writing the novels of William Faulkner impossible. This technology was named by Stuart Cramer after early models by John Gorrie and Edward Elis were perfected in 1902 in Buffalo, by Willis (20 pts)",
        "Carrier. These devices allowed for the post-war economic and population boom in the (10 pts)",
        "South. For 10 points, name these devices which use freon or other liquids to dehumidify and cool buildings."
      ],
      "answer": "air conditioners NHBB B 2014-2015"
    }
  ]
}